Guide to the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America records, 1914-1980.
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America records, 1914-1980.
- VIII. Executive officers' papers, 1914-1971. (Box 112-155)
  - A. Bessie Hillman correspondence, 1930-1970. (Box 112-120)
    - 1. General Correspondence 1930-70
      - B (general) (1937-69), Chester Bowles (U.S. House of Representatives) concerning the Chairman of the Platform and Resolutions Committee for the 1960 Democratic National Convention; Burt Beck regarding the assassination of Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.; Herman Badillo's (President, Borough of the Bronx) condolences upon the death of Milton Fried. (Box 112, Folder 12-13)
      - Chatman, Abraham (Manager, Rochester Joint Board) and Gertrude (1951-69), Discussions of personal and professional business. (Box 112, Folder 14)
      - Christman, Elizabeth (Secretary-Treasurer, National Women's Trade Union League (1947-67), Personal letters containing references to mutual friends. (Box 112, Folder 15)
      - Civil Liberties Clearing House (1952-69) (Box 112, Folder 16)
      - Consumers (National Association of) (1951-52) (Box 112, Folder 17)
      - Cortigene, Anthony (Manager, Philadelphia Joint Board) and Bobbie (1966-67), Personal and professional business. (Box 112, Folder 18)
      - C (general) (1935-68), Josephine Casey (Field Director, Industrial League for Equality); Rose Mary Coppola regarding workers' education, specifically the Husdon Shore School; Alice Cook (Professor, ILR-Cornell University) concerning a speaking engagement; Lewis Carliner's (UAW) "Statistical Reflections for a Discussion of Women's Problems." (Box 112, Folder 19-20)
      - D (general) (1930-70), Mary Dreier; David Dubinsky (President, ILGWU); Marcia Dunber-Soule regarding the death of her father; Democratic National Committee. (Box 112, Folder 21-22)
      - E (general) (1943-70), Memo from William Elkuss concerning the impact of Nixon's veto of the HEW bill. (Box 113, Folder 1)
      - Fried, Milton (1949-62) (Box 113, Folder 2)
      - F (general) (1938-69) (Box 113, Folder 3-4)
      - General Executive Board Memoranda (1960-63) (Box 113, Folder 5)
      - Goldberg, Arthur J. (Justice of the United States, The Supreme Court) and Dorothy (1961-70), Personal letters; discussion of the "labor movement's" failure to provide a home for retired people. (Box 113, Folder 6)
      - G (general) (1930-67), D.A. Gokhale's (Professor of History and founder, United National Society, Poona, India) discussion of the state of India and a request for aid. (Box 113, Folder 7)
      - Hall, Helen (National Association of Consumers,Inc.) (1939-58) (Box 113, Folder 8)
      - Herrick, Elinore (1946-60) (Box 113, Folder 9)
      - Hertz, Hugo (Hamburg, Germany) (1946-48), Anti-Semitism; the future of the Jewish people. (Box 113, Folder 10)
      - Herzog, Sarah (Chief Rabbi's Residence, Jerusalem) (1949-65) (Box 113, Folder 11)
      - Hillman, Sidney (1930-44), Telegrams. (Box 113, Folder 12)
      - Hillman, Sidney Foundation (1948-67) (Box 113, Folder 13)
      - H (general) (1937-70), Condolences to J.B.S. Hardman concerning Hannah; W. Averill Harriman (Governor, New York); William D. Hassett (Secretary to the President of the U.S.) concerning S.J. Res. 39 (Housing Rent Act of 1947); Dorothy I. Height (National President, National Council of Negro Women, Inc.); Margaret Hoening; Louis Hollander (President, N.Y. State CIO); Hudson Shore Labor School; Raymond M. Hilliard (Executive Director, Welfare and Health Council of New York City). (Box 113, Folder 14-15)
      - Independent Democrats (1949-50) (Box 113, Folder 16)
      - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU) (1957-67) (Box 113, Folder 17)
      - Israel trip (1952-53), Diary; articles; newspaper clippings; photograph, speech by Bessie Hillman "At the Opening of the Hillman Museum of the Amal School." (Box 113, Folder 18)
      - Ives, Irving M. (U.S. Senator) (1950-54), Co-sponsor of amendments to the Senate Judiciary Committee Displaced Persons Bill; school lunch programs; tax exemptions. (Box 113, Folder 19)
      - I (general) (1950-66), A. Isavitz and family; United Italian-American Labor Council, Inc.; Italo-American Committee of the Men's Clothing Industry. (Box 113, Folder 20)
      - Johnson, Mrs. Lyndon B. (Lady Bird) (1963-66) (Box 114, Folder 1)
      - Jones, Isabelle (Local 365, Atlanta, Georgia) (1948-52) (Box 114, Folder 2)
      - J (general) (1947-70), May Hall James (Chairman, American Section, Canadian-American Women's Committee) concerning an exchange program for undergraduate women. (Box 114, Folder 3)
      - Kennedy, Jacqueline (1960), Women's Committee for New Frontiers; New York Citizens for Kennedy and Johnson; Record of JFK on Civil Rights and Race Relations; Inauguration Day memorabilia. (Box 114, Folder 4)
      - Kenyon, Dorothy (Attorney, New York, N.Y.) (1944-64) Reference to "Senator McCarthy" (Joe) (Box 114, Folder 5)
      - K (general) (1944-69), Frank B. Keefe, M.C. (U.S. House of Representatives) regarding the liquidation of the Women's Bureau; Arthur G. Klein (U.S. House of Representatives) concerning H.R. 4567 (the revised Celler Bill); Harley M. Kilgore (U.S. Senate) about appropriations for rent control and S. 1016 (private bill on behalf of Boruch and Etla Rutenberg:) Marc Karson (Education Director, Amalgamated Summer Institute) regarding workers' education. (Box 114, Folder 6)
      - La Guardia House Nursery (1961-64) (Box 114, Folder 7)
      - Lehman, Herbert H. (U.S. Senate) (1946-60), H.R. 4567 (the revised Celler Bill); federal assistance toward school lunches; condolences to the family of Herbert H. Lehman. (Box 114, Folder 8)
      - Levin, Samuel (Chairman of the Board, Amalgamated Trust and Savings Bank) (1930-62) (Box 114, Folder 9)
      - L (general) (1940-70), Isador Lubin; Laurinburg Normal and Industrial Institute. (Box 114, Folder 10)
      - Mental Health (National Association for) (1953) (Box 114, Folder 11)
      - Miller, Frieda S. (Director, Women's Bureau, U.S. Department of Labor) (1950-52), Women's Congress in Haiti; a visit to the U.S. by women from the Ministry of Labor of Japan. (Box 114, Folder 12)
      - Minimum Wage Amendment (1948) (Box 114, Folder 13)
      - Myerson, Golda (Minister of Labor of the State of Israel) (1951) (Box 114, Folder 14)
      - M (general) (1935-69), George Marshall (Chairman, Civil Rights Congress) regarding the campaign to unseat Mississippi Senator Bilbo; Baltimore Regional Labor Board, ACWA Health and Welfare Fund builds first union-employer sponsored day care center; Frederic Methot (Promotion Director, WLIB) concerning the program "This Woman's World"; Earl C. Michener (U.S. House of Representatives) about the Stratton Bill (H.R. 2910) (displaced persons); Cpl. Frederic R. Mimms' (Presque Isle, Maine) description of working conditions in a small town laundry; condolences to the family of Henry Morgenthau Jr.; Esther Murray (Field Director, P.A.C.) concerning the agenda for a forthcoming CIO-PAC Women's Conference; Philip Murray; Thomas A. Murray (President, New York State Federation of Labor) on letters to State Senators and Assemblymen endorsing S.I. 216 and A.I. No. 252 (Minimum Wage) and A.I. 488 (Child Labor). (Box 114, Folder 15-16)
      - Newman, Pauline M. (1964-67), "Of Mary Anderson" (at Miss Anderson's memorial services ...). (Box 114, Folder 17)
      - N (general) (1946-70), National Consumers League; Maurice F. Neufeld (Professor of Industrial and Labor Relations, Cornell University); Cecyle S. Neidle (Historian); Bessie Hillman's speech to the New York Joint Board on the Occasion of the 50th Anniversary of the ACWA. (Box 114, Folder 18)
      - O'Dwyer, William (Mayor, City of New York) (1948-64) (Box 114, Folder 19)
      - O (general) (1947-66) (Box 114, Folder 20)
      - Pepper, Claude (U.S. Senator, Florida) (1949-51), S. 2580, a Private Bill, introduced on behalf of Boruck and Etla Rutenburg (cousins of Bessie Hillman), which would allow the Rutenburgs to settle in the U.S. or a least postpone deportation proceedings against them. (Box 115, Folder 1)
      - Peterson, Esther (Assistant Secretary, U.S. Department of Labor) (1947-69), Personal letters describing Esther Peterson's children and their family life in Sweden; biographical sketches of Danish Trade Union women who intend to visit the United States. (Box 115, Folder 2)
      - Posner, Jerome (Manager, Los Angeles Joint Board) (1945-53), Problem granting retirement benefits in the Harvey Ziperstein case indicates a "national office insurance problem." (Box 115, Folder 3)
      - Potofsky, Jacob B. (General President, ACWA) (1937-68), Letter to Elliott V. Bill (Editor and Publisher, Business Week) criticizing "Labor Violence and Corruption" (8/31/57) for failing to distinguish between honest and corrupt unions, as well as smearing Sidney Hillman and the ACWA. (Box 115, Folder 4)
      - P-Q (general) (1933-67), Rose P. Parsons (President, National Council of Women) regarding a meeting with Mrs. Roosevelt (Eleanor) to discuss a Russian exchange; Bessie Hillman's request that Mr. Howard (Franklin Specialty Co. and former American Labor Party member) sign a collective bargaining contract with ACWA; Inwood House; People's Committee for Mental Hygiene; Miss Jennie Previti's concern for old age benefits; Pennrae Protective Association; Justine Wise Polier; Richard R. Pigrone's (Local 102, Boston Joint Board) praise for Matthew Josephson's biography of Sidney Hillman. (Box 115, Folder 5)
      - Randolph, A. Philip (and Institute) (1951-69) (Box 115, Folder 6)
      - Reilly, Ethel W. (retiree, M.A. Seinsheimer Co.) (1961-70), The welfare of retirees. (Box 115, Folder 7)
      - Reuther, Walter P. (President, UAW) (1948-70) (Box 115, Folder 8)
      - Robins, Raymond (Colonel) (husband of Margaret Dreier Robins) (1945), Condolence letter upon the death of Margaret Dreier Robins. (Box 115, Folder 9)
      - Robinson, Dollie Lowther (Special Assistant to the Director, Women's Bureau, U.S. Department of Labor) (1944-67), CIO organizing drive in the South; personal family news; material on the Dewey Administration, (also contains reference to Margaret Sanger.) (See also box 115, file folders 21-22 for Milton D. Stewart letter.) (Box 115, Folder 10)
      - Roosevelt, Eleanor (1948-67), National Issues Committee; James Roosevelt regarding the Eleanor Roosevelt Institute for Cancer Research; Wiltwyck School (See also box 119, file folder 2 for other Eleanor Roosevelt correspondence.) (Box 115, Folder 11)
      - Rothbart, Isadore and Ida (1947-57), Letters mixing personal and professional business. (Box 115, Folder 12)
      - R (general) (1930-69), Mortimer C. Ritter (Needlecraft Educational Commission); Henry Richmond (journalist and son of Sam Diamond; David Rapport concerning his niece Kato Gluck (a concentration camp survivor); Philip R. Rogers (Staff Director, U.S. Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare) regarding Senate Bill 1567 (Migratory Labor Bill); Anna Romeo's (recently diagnosed as having diabetes) request for assistance finding a job; condolence letter from Daniel Rajzman (Santurce, P.R.) upon the death of Milton Fried. (Box 115, Folder 13)
      - Salerno, Joseph (Regional Director, New England Regional Office, ACWA) (1950-70), Polly Buttrick's (University of Vermont student) response to Joseph Salerno's speech. (Box 115, Folder 14)
      - Sandburg, Carl (Connemara Farm, Flat Rock, N.C.) (1961), Bessie Hillman's reminiscence of meeting Sandburg. (Box 115, Folder 15)
      - Schlossberg, Joseph (General Secretary-Treasurer, ACWA) (1938-49), Arranging for Bessie Hillman's sister and family to come from Montreal to the U.S. (Box 115, Folder 16)
      - Schneiderman, Rose (New York Women's Trade Union League) (1949), Rose Schneiderman: A Tribute (upon her retirement from the NYWTUL) by Bessie Hillman. (Box 115, Folder 17)
      - Smith, Hilda W. (Consultant, Office of Economic Opportunity) (1965-69), Personal news; poems. (Box 115, Folder 18)
      - Stevenson, Adlai (Campaign) (1956-60), Agnes E. Meyer's speech "The Importance of Labor Unions in American Politics" before the 22nd Biennial Convention of the ACWA; reprints from The New Republic and U.S. News and World Report; newspaper clips; memorabilia. (Box 115, Folder 19)
      - Szold, Robert (1948-69), Possible libel suit against American Mercury for a comment made against Sidney Hillman. (Box 115, Folder 20)
      - S (general) (1935-70), "John Sparkman (U.S. Senator and Chairman, Subcommittee on Housing and Rents) regarding a Rent Control Bill; Leverett Saltonstall (U.S. Senator) concerning federal rent control; condolences to Mrs. Lawrence Steinhardt (American Embassy, Ottawa, Ontario) upon the death of her husband; Annabelle Sweeney (Atlanta Joint Board); condolences to Mrs. Henry L. Stimson upon the death of her husband; letter in Yiddish from Mrs. Y. Sardatsky; Milton D. Stewart (State of New York Administrative Assistant Counsel to the Governor) about recommending Dollie Lowther-Robinson for the position of Secretary of the Department of Labor (New York State) (also see box 115, file folder 10 Robinson, Dollie Lowther); memo from J.J. Shoaff on ""Clothing Workers and Their Dependents Insurance Coverage and Retirement Benefits;"" poetry by Thomas Shpritzer; Sargent Shriver regarding the war against poverty; David H. Strong (Greenbelt, MD) concerning an oil painting of Sidney Hillman; Robert T. Snyder (Counsel at law) regarding Hillman versus Balmoral Hotel. (Box 115, Folder 21-22)
      - Truman, Harry S. (1946-48), Hartley Bill. (Box 115A, Folder 1)
      - T (general) (1934-67), Cora Thomas (clothing worker, Reading, Penn.) concerning shop closings; Gladys A. Tillett (U.S. Representative on the United Nations Commission on the Status of Women) regarding use of a quotation from Bessie Hillman's "Gifted Women in Trade Unions" in American Women: The Changing Image. (Box 115A, Folder 2)
      - Union Label Campaign (ACWA) (1949-54) (Box 115A, Folder 3-4)
      - U (general) (1949-66), Photo taken at the clothing dinner in behalf of the United Jewish Appeal. (Box 115A, Folder 5)
      - V (general) (1944-65) (Box 115A, Folder 6)
      - Wagner, Robert F. Jr. (1953-58), Condolences upon the death of Robert F. Wagner. (Box 115A, Folder 7)
      - Weinstein, Charles (Philadelphia Joint Board) (1949-51), Marriage of Charles Weinstein's daughter; dedication of the Sidney Hillman Medical Center of the Philadelphia Male Apparel Industry. (Box 115A, Folder 8)
      - Werts, Leo R. (Director, Office of Military Government for Germany, U.S. Manpower Division, Berlin, Germany) (1948-49), Personal and professional business. (Box 115A, Folder 9)
      - W (general) (1944-70), Theodore S. Weiss (Councilman, 3rd District, New York, N.Y.); Weizmann Institute of Science; Barbara Wertheimer; "Victory Marching Song of the A.C.W.A." by Henry W. Wise; James Waterman Wise's (Director, Council Against Intolerance in America) draft of the pamphlet "Your Right to Work"; Henry Wolchin regarding retirement benefits; Leonard Woodcock (President, UAW); Dr. Chaim Weizmann (President, Provisional Government of Israel) and "Salute to the President of Israel." (Box 115A, Folder 10-11)
      - X, Z, Y (general) (1944-50), William Zuckerman. (Box 115A, Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous - unidentified correspondence (1932-69), Charlie and Florence; Cricket; Esther and Pauldi; Julie; Dora; Richard; Electa; Mabel; Priscilla and Daniel. (Box 115A, Folder 13)
      - A-Z, Condolence letters (1946 upon the death of Sidney Hillman) (Box 116)
    - 2. Commissions and Committee Work 1940-66, Routine commission and committee documents include: minutes, resolutions, officers' reports, financial reports, newsletters, news releases, articles, pamphlets, leaflets and miscellaneous items generated by the commission or committee. Arranged alphabetically by commission or committee and chronologically within each folder.
      - AFL-CIO Civil Rights Commission (1956-60), Routine commission documents; report on civil rights legislation; AFL-CIO Executive Council's statement on "The Situation in Little Rock, Arkansas." (Box 117, Folder 1)
      - CIO Civil Rights Committee/ Committee to Abolish Discrimination (1940-54), Routine committee documents; "Facts in the Case of Roosevelt Ward Jr.;" interview with James B. Carey (Secretary-Treasurer, CIO); excerpt from Walter Reuther testimony before the House Committee on Education and Labor; manuscript entitled The AFL and Racial Discrimination by the International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers - CIO; memorandum to the Attorney General on "Administrative Action to Improve the Civil Rights Machinery of the Department of Justice;" NAACP statement on labor policy; Executive Order Establishing the Government Contract Committee; memorandum to the Attorney General on "Implementation of the Non-Discrimination Provision in Government Contracts." (Box 117, Folder 2-3)
      - CIO Community Service Committee (CIO-CSC) (1949-57), Routine committee documents; civil defense; campaign for Korea; from Phil Fried to Leo Perlis (National Director, CIO-CSC) about becoming a volunteer representative of the National CIO-CSC; speech of Joseph Curran (President, National Maritime Union, CIO) at the Greater New York Fund Forum; summary report on the National Strike Assistance Workshop; Brewery Workers Local Union No. 9 Strike Counselling Institute (pamphlet); list of contributions to the National CIO-CSC for Holland food relief; Milwaukee County Industrial Union Council CSC Advanced Counsellor Training Institute - Workman's Compensation; Health and Welfare Advisory Council; partial report on the Merck Strike in Rahway, N.J.; CIO-CSC leaflets. (Box 117, Folder 4-7)
      - Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services (1940-66), Routine committee documents; letter from George C. Marshall (Secretary of Defense) appointing Bessie Hillman to the committee; "Restricted" report, Women in the Air Force: A Study of Recent Enlistees; itineraries of committee tours and field trips; "Restricted" report, Attitudes of Civilian Groups in the State of Illinois Toward Women in the Service; "Restricted" report Enlisted Women in the Services: III. Some Satisfactions and Dissatisfactions of Service Life; Bessie Hillman's resignation from the committee; memorandum on "Non-Discrimination Policy and the Bureau of Employment Security;" "Survey of Employment Prospects for Negroes in Armament Industries." (Box 118, Folder 1-6)
      - Democratic Advisory Council (Advisory Committee on Labor Policy) (1957-61), Routine committee documents. (Box 119, Folder 1)
      - President's Commission on the Status of Women/ Committee on Protective Legislation (1960-63), Routine committee documents; Executive Order 10980 Establishing the President's Commission on the Status of Women; Information Paper on Federal and State Laws Governing Employment of Women; letter welcoming Bessie Hillman to the commission from Eleanor Roosevelt (See also box 115, file folder 11, for other Eleanor Roosevelt correspondence;) biographical sketches of members of the Committee on Protective Legislation; minimum wage laws; article entitled "The Role of Protective Legislation" from Women Today: Trends and Issues by Dr. Caroline F. Wise; U.S. Department of Labor publications; drafts and final Report of the Committee on Protective Labor Legislation to the President's Commission on the Status of Women; advanced copy and final bound edition of American Women, the Report of the President's Commission on the Status of Women. (Box 119, Folder 2-5)
      - President's Conference on Industrial Safety (1950-51), Routine conference documents. (Box 119, Folder 6)
      - Welfare Council of New York City (1948-49), Routine council documents; report of the Committee on Puerto Ricans in New York City; Digest Report on Central Harlem Street Clubs Project. (Box 119, Folder 7)
    - 3. Printed, Pamphlet Material (1946-70)
      - Printed, Pamphlet Material, Supreme Court Brief of Elmer W. Henderson, Appellant v. The United States of America, Interstate Commerce Commission and Southern Railway Company; Report of the National Education Department to the General Executive Board, ACWA; Problems of Working Women: A Summary Report of A Conference Sponsored by Industrial Union Department AFL-CIO; This is the Record: Re-elect Herbert H. Lehman United States Senator; "Exhibit E. Eligibility Requirements" (ACWA retirement plan). (Box 120, Folder 1-2)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 120, Folder 3-4)
  - B. Jacob Potofsky. Assistant President and Secretary-Treasurer's correspondence, 1930-1946., Correspondence documenting Jacob Potofsky's activities while serving in several capacities for the ACWA, including assistan president and assistant general secretary-treasurer. This correspondence mainly concerns union organizing, various locals and joint boards of the ACWA, relations with garment manufacturers, and relations with other labor organizations in the U.S. and abroad. The bulk of the correspondence dates from the 1930s; consequently, materials on topics such as relief for unemployed workers from charitable organizations and labor-led anti-fascist activities are also represented. Other topics covered include: worker education; consumer organizations; government agencies (in particular the NRA); and politicians, political organizations, and political campaigns.; Individuals represented in the collection include: Mary Anderson; Alben Barkley; August Bellanca; Dorothy Jacobs Bellanca; Sidney Hillman; David Dubinsky; Fiorello LaGuardia; John L. Lewis; Tom Mooney; Joseph Schlossberg; Rose Schneiderman; Robert F. Wagner; and Matthew Woll.; Major organizations represented include: the AFL; the American Labor Party; Brookwood Labor College; Consumers Union; the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; the Jewish Daily Forward; the Jewish Labor Committee; Labor's Non-Partisan League; the National Consumers' League; the National Labor Relations Board; the National Recovery Administration; the Rand School of Social Science; the U.S. Dept. of Labor; the United Textile Workers of America; the Works Progress Administration; and various subordinate units of the ACWA. (Box 121-128)
    - Abt, John (ACWA attorney) 1938-40 (Box 121, Folder 1)
    - Addes, George (UAW) 1938-39 (Box 121, Folder 2)
    - Advance (1937) re Frank Rosenblum and the midwestern organizing campaign (Box 121, Folder 3)
    - Aluminum Workers of America (1937) (Box 121, Folder 4)
    - Altschuler, Michael (Corregated Enterprises) 1936 (Box 121, Folder 5)
    - Amalgamated Housing Corporation (including correspondence with A.E. Kazan) 1937-39 (Box 121, Folder 6)
    - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (letters to GEB and Dept. heads) (Box 121, Folder 7)
    - ACWA (letters to locals and joint boards) 1937-38 (Box 121, Folder 8)
    - Amalgamated Securities (1942) (Box 121, Folder 9)
    - Amalgamated Trust and Savings Bank of Chicago (1936) (Box 121, Folder 10)
    - American Arbitration Association (1938) (Box 121, Folder 11)
    - American Federation of Labor (correspondence with William Green and Frank Morrison re jurisdictional problems, union label and Norfolk strike) 1935-36 (Box 121, Folder 12)
    - American Labor Party (1936-44) correspondence with Elinor Herrick, state campaign director, Alex Rose, secretary regarding state election campaigns (Box 121, Folder 13-17)
    - American Russian Chamber of Commerce (1933) (Box 121, Folder 18)
    - Anderson, Mary (1935-36) (Box 121, Folder 19)
    - Andrews, John (American Association for Labor Legislation) 1935 (Box 121, Folder 20)
    - Anthracite Coal district student letters to Jacob Potofsky (1939) (Box 121, Folder 21)
    - Asher, Benjamin (manufacturer, Fitchberg, Mississippi) 1939 (Box 121, Folder 22)